Logical Sequence of Words
In each of the following questions, arrange the given words in a meaningful sequence and thus find the correct answer from alternatives.
[{'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Key 2. Door 3. Lock\n4. Room 5. Switch on  ', 'options': ['5, 1, 2, 4, 3', '4, 2, 1, 5, 3', '1, 3, 2, 4, 5', '1, 2, 3, 5, 4'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Word 2. Paragraph 3. Sentence\n4. Letters 5. Phrase  ', 'options': ['4, 1, 5, 2, 3', '4, 1, 3, 5, 2', '4, 2, 5, 1, 3', '4, 1, 5, 3, 2'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Police 2. Punishment 3. Crime\n4. Judge 5. Judgement  ', 'options': ['3, 1, 2, 4, 5', '1, 2, 4, 3, 5', '5, 4, 3, 2, 1', '3, 1, 4, 5, 2'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Family 2. Community 3. Member\n4. Locality 5. Country  ', 'options': ['3, 1, 2, 4, 5', '3, 1, 2, 5, 4', '3, 1, 4, 2, 5', '3, 1, 4, 5, 2'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Poverty 2. Population 3. Death\n4. Unemployment 5. Disease  ', 'options': ['2, 3, 4, 5, 1', '3, 4, 2, 5, 1', '2, 4, 1, 5, 3', '1, 2, 3, 4, 5'], 'answer': 'c'}]
In each of the following questions, arrange the given words in a meaningful sequence and thus find the correct answer from alternatives.
[{'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Leaf 2. Fruit 3. Stem\n4. Root 5. Flower  ', 'options': ['3, 4, 5, 1, 2', '4, 3, 1, 5, 2', '4, 1, 3, 5, 2', '4, 3, 1, 2, 5'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Nation 2. Village 3. City\n4. District 5. State  ', 'options': ['2, 3, 4, 5, 1', '2, 3, 4, 1, 5', '1, 3, 5, 4, 2', '1, 2, 3, 4, 5'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Caste 2. Family 3. Newly married Couple\n4. Clan 5. Species  ', 'options': ['2, 3, 1, 4, 5', '3, 4, 5, 1, 2', '3, 2, 1, 4, 5', '4, 5, 3, 2, 1'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Cut 2. Put on 3. Mark\n4. Measure 5. Tailor  ', 'options': ['3, 1, 5, 4, 2', '2, 4, 3, 1, 5', '1, 3, 2, 4, 5', '4, 3, 1, 5, 2'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. House 2. Street 3. Room\n4. Town 5. District  ', 'options': ['3, 2, 1, 4, 5', '3, 1, 4, 2, 5', '3, 1, 2, 4, 5', '3, 1, 2, 5, 4'], 'answer': 'c'}]
In each of the following questions, arrange the given words in a meaningful sequence and thus find the correct answer from alternatives.
[{'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Wall 2. Clay 3. House\n4. Room 5. Bricks  ', 'options': ['5, 2, 1, 4, 3', '2, 5, 4, 1, 3', '2, 5, 1, 4, 3', '1, 2, 3, 4, 5'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Probation 2. Interview 3. Selection\n4. Appointment 5. Advertisement 6. Application', 'options': ['5, 6, 3, 2, 4, 1', '5, 6, 4, 2, 3, 1', '5, 6, 2, 3, 4, 1', '6, 5, 4, 2, 3, 1'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Elephant 2. Cat 3. Mosquito\n4. Tiger 5. Whale  ', 'options': ['5, 3, 1, 2, 4', '3, 2, 4, 1, 5', '1, 3, 5, 4, 2', '2, 5, 1, 4, 3'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Yarn 2. Plant 3. Saree\n4. Cotton 5. Cloth  ', 'options': ['2, 4, 5, 1, 3', '2, 4, 3, 5, 1', '2, 4, 1, 5, 3', '2, 4, 5, 3, 1'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Infant 2. Old 3. Adult\n4. Adolescent 5. Child  ', 'options': ['5, 4, 3, 2, 1', '3, 4, 2, 1, 5', '2, 3, 4, 5, 1', '1, 5, 4, 3, 2'], 'answer': 'd'}]
In each of the following questions, arrange the given words in a meaningful sequence and thus find the correct answer from alternatives.
[{'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Leaves 2. Branch 3. Flower\n4. Tree 5. Fruit  ', 'options': ['4, 3, 1, 2, 5', '4, 2, 5, 1, 3', '4, 3, 2, 1, 5', '4, 2, 1, 3, 5'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Tree 2. Seed 3. Flowers\n4. Fruit 5. Plant  ', 'options': ['5, 2, 1, 3, 4', '2, 5, 1, 4, 3', '2, 5, 1, 3, 4', '2, 5, 3, 1, 4'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Adult 2. Child 3. Infant\n4. Boy 5. Adolescent  ', 'options': ['1, 3, 4, 5, 2', '2, 3, 5, 4, 1', '2, 3, 4, 1, 5', '3, 2, 4, 5, 1'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Protect 2. Pressure 3. Relief\n4. Rain 5. Flood  ', 'options': ['2, 4, 3, 1, 5', '2, 4, 5, 1, 3', '2, 5, 4, 1, 3', '3, 2, 4, 5, 1'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Presentation 2. Recommendation 3. Arrival\n4. Discussion 5. Introduction  ', 'options': ['5, 3, 4, 1, 2', '3, 5, 4, 2, 1', '3, 5, 1, 4, 2', '5, 3, 1, 2, 4'], 'answer': 'c'}]
In each of the following questions, arrange the given words in a meaningful sequence and thus find the correct answer from alternatives.
[{'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Income 2. Status 3. Education\n4. Well-being 5. Job  ', 'options': ['3, 1, 5, 2, 4', '1, 3, 2, 5, 4', '1, 2, 5, 3, 4', '3, 5, 1, 2, 4'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Heel 2. Shoulder 3. Skull 4. Neck 5. Knee\n6. Chest 7. Thigh 8. Stomach 9. Face 10. Hand', 'options': ['3, 4, 7, 9, 2, 5, 8, 10, 6, 1', '3, 9, 4, 2, 10, 6, 8, 7, 5, 1', '2, 4, 7, 10, 1, 5, 8, 9, 6, 3', '4, 7, 10, 1, 9, 6, 2, 5, 8, 3'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Arrange the words given below in a meaningful sequence.\n1. Rainbow 2. Rain 3. Sun\n4. Happy 5. Child  ', 'options': ['4, 2, 3, 5, 1', '2, 3, 1, 5, 4', '4, 5, 1, 2, 3', '2, 1, 4, 5, 3'], 'answer': 'b'}]

Blood Relation Test
[{'question': 'Pointing to a photograph of a boy Suresh said, "He is the son of the only son of my mother." How is Suresh related to that boy?', 'options': ['Brother', 'Uncle', 'Cousin', 'Father'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'If A + B means A is the mother of B; A - B means A is the brother B; A % B means A is the father of B and A x B means A is the sister of B, which of the following shows that P is the maternal uncle of Q?', 'options': ['Q - N + M x P', 'P + S x N - Q', 'P - M + N x Q', 'Q - S % P'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'If A is the brother of B; B is the sister of C; and C is the father of D, how D is related to A?', 'options': ['Brother', 'Sister', 'Nephew', 'Cannot be determined'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'If A + B means A is the brother of B; A - B means A is the sister of B and A x B means A is the father of B. Which of the following means that C is the son of M?', 'options': ['M - N x C + F', 'F - C + N x M', 'N + M - F x C', 'M x N - C + F'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Introducing a boy, a girl said, "He is the son of the daughter of the father of my uncle." How is the boy related to the girl?', 'options': ['Brother', 'Nephew', 'Uncle', 'Son-in-law'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Pointing to a photograph Lata says, "He is the son of the only son of my grandfather." How is the man in the photograph related to Lata?', 'options': ['Brother', 'Uncle', 'Cousin', 'Data is inadequate'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'If A + B means A is the brother of B; A x B means A is the son of B; and A % B means B is the daughter of A then which of the following means M is the maternal uncle of N?', 'options': ['M + O x N', 'M % O x N + P', 'M + O % N', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'If D is the brother of B, how B is related to C? To answer this question which of the statements is/are necessary?\nThe son of D is the grandson of C.\nB is the sister of D.', 'options': ['Only 1', 'Only 2', 'Either 1 or 2', '1 and 2 both are required'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'If A + B means A is the father of B; A - B means A is the brother B; A % B means A is the wife of B and A x B means A is the mother of B, which of the following shows that M is the maternal grandmother of T?', 'options': ['M x N % S + T', 'M x N - S % T', 'M x S - N % T', 'M x N x S % T'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Pointing to a photograph. Bajpai said, "He is the son of the only daughter of the father of my brother." How Bajpai is related to the man in the photograph?', 'options': ['Nephew', 'Brother', 'Father', 'Maternal Uncle'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Deepak said to Nitin, "That boy playing with the football is the younger of the two brothers of the daughter of my father\'s wife." How is the boy playing football related to Deepak?', 'options': ['Son', 'Brother', 'Cousin', 'Brother-in-law'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Pointing a photograph X said to his friend Y, "She is the only daughter of the father of my mother." How X is related to the person of photograph?', 'options': ['Daughter', 'Son', 'Nephew', 'Cannot be decided'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Veena who is the sister-in-law of Ashok, is the daughter-in-law of Kalyani. Dheeraj is the father of Sudeep who is the only brother of Ashok. How Kalyani is related to Ashok?', 'options': ['Mother-in-law', 'Aunt', 'Wife', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'If A + B means A is the sister of B; A x B means A is the wife of B, A % B means A is the father of B and A - B means A is the brother of B. Which of the following means T is the daughter of P?', 'options': ['P x Q % R + S - T', 'P x Q % R - T + S', 'P x Q % R + T - S', 'P x Q % R + S + T'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Pointing to a woman, Abhijit said, "Her granddaughter is the only daughter of my brother." How is the woman related to Abhijit?', 'options': ['Sister', 'Grandmother', 'Mother-in-law', 'Mother'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Amit said - "This girl is the wife of the grandson of my mother". How is Amit related to the girl?', 'options': ['Brother', 'Grandfather', 'Husband', 'Father-in-law'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'A and B are children of D. Who is the father of A? To answer this question which of the statements (1) and (2) is necessary?\nC is the brother of A and the son of E.\nF is the mother B.', 'options': ['Only (1)', 'Only (2)', 'Either (1) or (2)', '(1) and (2) both'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Pointing towards a man, a woman said, "His mother is the only daughter of my mother." How is the woman related to the man?', 'options': ['Mother', 'Grandmother', 'Sister', 'Daughter'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'If P $ Q means P is the brother of Q; P # Q means P is the mother of Q; P * Q means P is the daughter of Q in A # B $ C * D, who is the father?', 'options': ['D', 'B', 'C', 'Data is inadequate'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Introducing Sonia, Aamir says, "She is the wife of only nephew of only brother of my mother." How Sonia is related to Aamir?', 'options': ['Wife', 'Sister', 'Sister-in-law', 'Data is inadequate'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'If A + B means A is the brother of B; A % B means A is the father of B and A x B means A is the sister of B. Which of the following means M is the uncle of P?', 'options': ['M % N x P', 'N x P % M', 'M + S % R % P', 'M + K % T x P'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Pointing to Varman, Madhav said, "I am the only son of one of the sons of his father." How is Varman related to Madhav?', 'options': ['Nephew', 'Uncle', 'Father or Uncle', 'Father'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Introducing a woman, Shashank said, "She is the mother of the only daughter of my son." How that woman is related to Shashank?', 'options': ['Daughter', 'Sister-in-law', 'Wife', 'Daughter-in-law'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'If A + B means B is the brother of A; A x B means B is the husband of A; A - B means A is the mother of B and A % B means A is the father of B, which of the following relations shows that Q is the grandmother of T?', 'options': ['Q - P + R % T', 'P x Q % R - T', 'P x Q % R + T', 'P + Q % R - T'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'A3P means A is the mother of P\nA4P means A is the brother of P\nA9P means A is the husband of P\nA5P means A is the daughter of P\nWhich of the following means that K is the mother-in-law of M?', 'options': ['M9N3K4J', 'M9N5K3J', 'K5J9M3N', 'K3J9N4M'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Pointing to a photograph Anjali said, "He is the son of the only son of my grandfather." How is the man in the photograph related to Anjali?', 'options': ['Brother', 'Uncle', 'Son', 'Data is inadequate'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Pointing to a person, Deepak said, "His only brother is the father of my daughter\'s father". How is the person related to Deepak?', 'options': ['Father', 'Grandfather', 'Uncle', 'Brother-in-law'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'P is the mother of K; K is the sister of D; D is the father of J. How is P related to J?', 'options': ['Mother', 'Grandmother', 'Aunt', 'Data inadequate'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'If P $ Q means P is the father of Q; P # Q means P is the mother of Q and P * Q means P is the sister of Q, then N # L $ P * Q shows which of the relation of Q to N?', 'options': ['Grand son', 'Grand daughter', 'Nephew', 'Data is inadequate'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'If A $ B means A is the brother of B; A @ B means A is the wife of B; A # B means A is the daughter of B and A * B means A is the father of B, which of the following indicates that U is the father-in-law of P?', 'options': ['P @ Q $ T # U * W', 'P @ W $ Q * T # U', 'P @ Q $ W * T # U', 'P @ Q $ T # W * U'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Introducing a man, a woman said, "He is the only son of the mother of my mother." How is the woman related to the man?', 'options': ['Mother', 'Sister', 'Niece', 'Maternal aunt'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Pointing to Gopi, Nalni says, "I am the daughter of the only son of his grandfather." How Nalni is related to Gopi?', 'options': ['Niece', 'Daughter', 'Sister', 'Cannot be determined'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': "A's son B is married with C whose sister D is married to E the brother of B. How D is related to A?", 'options': ['Sister', "Daughter's-in-law", 'Sister-in-law', 'Cousin'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Pointing to a lady a person said, "The son of her only brother is the brother of my wife." How is the lady related to the person?', 'options': ['Maternal aunt', 'Grandmother', 'Sister of father-in-law', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'B5D means B is the father of D.\nB9D means B is the sister of D.\nB4D means B is the brother of D.\nB3D means B is the wife of D.\nWhich of the following means F is the mother of K?', 'options': ['F3M5K', 'F5M3K', 'F9M4N3K', 'F3M5N3K'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'A $ B means A is the father of B; A # B means A is the sister of B; A * B means A is the daughter of B and A @ B means A is the brother of B. Which of the following indicates that M is the wife of Q?', 'options': ['Q $ R # T @ M', 'Q $ R @ T # M', 'Q $ R * T # M', 'Q $ R @ T * M'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'If A $ B means A is the brother of B; B * C means B is the son of C; C @ D means C is the wife of D and A # D means A is the son of D, how C is related to A?', 'options': ['Maternal grandmother', 'Maternal aunt', 'Aunt', 'Mother'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Pointing to a girl Sandeep said, "She is the daughter of the only sister of my father." How is sandeep related to the girl?', 'options': ['Uncle', 'Cousin', 'Father', 'Grandfather'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Pointing to a boy in the photograph Reena said, "He is the only son of the only child of my grandfather." How Reena is related to that boy?', 'options': ['Mother', 'Sister', 'Aunt', 'Cannot be determined'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'A * B means A is the sister of B\nA $ B means B is the mother of A\nA + B means A is the brother of B\nA = B means B is the father of A.\nWhich of the following means M is the maternal uncle of N?', 'options': ['M = P + Q * N', 'N + P = Q * M', 'N * P $ Q * M', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'If M x N means M is the daughter of N; M + N means M is the father of N; M % N means M is the mother of N and M - N means M is the brother of N then P % Q + R - T x K indicates which relation of P to K?', 'options': ['Daughter-in-law', 'Sister-in-law', 'Aunt', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'If P + Q means P is the brother of Q; P x Q means P is the father of Q and P - Q means P is the sister of Q, which of the following relations shows that I is the niece of K?', 'options': ['K + Y + Z - I', 'K + Y x I - Z', 'Z - I x Y + K', 'K x Y + I - Z'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Pointing towards a girl, Abhisek says, "This girl is the daughter of only a child of my father." What is the relation of Abhisek\'s wife to that girl?', 'options': ['Daughter', 'Mother', 'Aunt', 'Sister'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'If A $ B means B is the father of A; A # B means B is the mother of A; A * B means B is the sister of A and A @ B means B is the husband of A, which of the following indicates that N is the grandmother of P?', 'options': ['P * Q # M $ N', 'P @ Q $ M # N', 'P # Q $ N * M', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Anupam said to a lady sitting in a car, "The only daughter of the brother of my wife is the sister-in-law of the brother of your sister." How the husband of the lady is related to Anupam?', 'options': ['Maternal uncle', 'Uncle', 'Father', 'Son-in-law'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'If P + Q means P is the brother of Q; P x Q means P is the wife of Q and P % Q means P is the daughter of Q then which of the following means D is the uncle of A?', 'options': ['A % B x C + D', 'A x B + C % D', 'A + C % B x D', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'A is the son of C; C and Q are sisters; Z is the mother of Q and P is the son of Z. Which of the following statements is true?', 'options': ['P and A are cousins', 'P is the maternal uncle of A', 'Q is the maternal grandfather of A', 'C and P are sisters'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'M is the father of N who is the son of V. In order to know the relation of M to P, which of the statement/statements is/are necessary?\nP is the brother of V.\nThe daughter of N is the granddaughter of V.', 'options': ['Only (1)', 'Only (2)', 'Either (1) or (2)', '(1) and (2) both'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'If X + Y means X is the daughter of Y; X - Y means X is the brother of Y; X % Y means X is the father of Y and X x Y means X is the sister of Y. Which of the following means I is the niece of J?', 'options': ['J - N % C x I', 'I x C - N % J', 'J + M x C % I', 'I x C + N - J'], 'answer': 'd'}]

Syllogism
In each of the following questions two statements are given and these statements are followed by two conclusions numbered (1) and (2). You have to take the given two statements to be true even if they seem to be at variance from commonly known facts. Read the conclusions and then decide which of the given conclusions logically follows from the two given statements, disregarding commonly known facts.
Give answer:
(A) If only (1) conclusion follows
(B) If only (2) conclusion follows
(C) If either (1) or (2) follows
(D) If neither (1) nor (2) follows and
(E) If both (1) and (2) follow.
[{'question': 'Statements: Some actors are singers. All the singers are dancers.\nConclusions:\nSome actors are dancers.\nNo singer is actor.', 'options': ['Only (1) conclusion follows', 'Only (2) conclusion follows', 'Either (1) or (2) follows', 'Neither (1) nor (2) follows', 'Both (1) and (2) follow'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Statements: All the harmoniums are instruments. All the instruments are flutes.\nConclusions:\nAll the flutes are instruments.\nAll the harmoniums are flutes.', 'options': ['Only (1) conclusion follows', 'Only (2) conclusion follows', 'Either (1) or (2) follows', 'Neither (1) nor (2) follows', 'Both (1) and (2) follow'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Statements: Some mangoes are yellow. Some tixo are mangoes.\nConclusions:\nSome mangoes are green.\nTixo is a yellow.', 'options': ['Only (1) conclusion follows', 'Only (2) conclusion follows', 'Either (1) or (2) follows', 'Neither (1) nor (2) follows', 'Both (1) and (2) follow'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Statements: Some ants are parrots. All the parrots are apples.\nConclusions:\nAll the apples are parrots.\nSome ants are apples.', 'options': ['Only (1) conclusion follows', 'Only (2) conclusion follows', 'Either (1) or (2) follows', 'Neither (1) nor (2) follows', 'Both (1) and (2) follow'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Statements: Some papers are pens. All the pencils are pens.\nConclusions:\nSome pens are pencils.\nSome pens are papers.', 'options': ['Only (1) conclusion follows', 'Only (2) conclusion follows', 'Either (1) or (2) follows', 'Neither (1) nor (2) follows', 'Both (1) and (2) follow'], 'answer': 'e'}]
In each of the following questions two statements are given and these statements are followed by two conclusions numbered (1) and (2). You have to take the given two statements to be true even if they seem to be at variance from commonly known facts. Read the conclusions and then decide which of the given conclusions logically follows from the two given statements, disregarding commonly known facts.
Give answer:
(A) If only (1) conclusion follows
(B) If only (2) conclusion follows
(C) If either (1) or (2) follows
(D) If neither (1) nor (2) follows and
(E) If both (1) and (2) follow.
[{'question': 'Statements: All the actors are girls. All the girls are beautiful.\nConclusions:\nAll the actors are beautiful.\nSome girls are actors.', 'options': ['Only (1) conclusion follows', 'Only (2) conclusion follows', 'Either (1) or (2) follows', 'Neither (1) nor (2) follows', 'Both (1) and (2) follow'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Statements: All the windows are doors. No door is a wall.\nConclusions:\nSome windows are walls.\nNo wall is a door.', 'options': ['Only (1) conclusion follows', 'Only (2) conclusion follows', 'Either (1) or (2) follows', 'Neither (1) nor (2) follows', 'Both (1) and (2) follow'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Statements: All cups are books. All books are shirts.\nConclusions:\nSome cups are not shirts.\nSome shirts are cups.', 'options': ['Only (1) conclusion follows', 'Only (2) conclusion follows', 'Either (1) or (2) follows', 'Neither (1) nor (2) follows', 'Both (1) and (2) follow'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Statements: Some cows are crows. Some crows are elephants.\nConclusions:\nSome cows are elephants.\nAll crows are elephants.', 'options': ['Only (1) conclusion follows', 'Only (2) conclusion follows', 'Either (1) or (2) follows', 'Neither (1) nor (2) follows', 'Both (1) and (2) follow'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Statements: All the pencils are pens. All the pens are inks.\nConclusions:\nAll the pencils are inks.\nSome inks are pencils.', 'options': ['Only (1) conclusion follows', 'Only (2) conclusion follows', 'Either (1) or (2) follows', 'Neither (1) nor (2) follows', 'Both (1) and (2) follow'], 'answer': 'e'}]
In each of the following questions two statements are given and these statements are followed by two conclusions numbered (1) and (2). You have to take the given two statements to be true even if they seem to be at variance from commonly known facts. Read the conclusions and then decide which of the given conclusions logically follows from the two given statements, disregarding commonly known facts.
Give answer:
(A) If only (1) conclusion follows
(B) If only (2) conclusion follows
(C) If either (1) or (2) follows
(D) If neither (1) nor (2) follows and
(E) If both (1) and (2) follow.
[{'question': 'Statements: Some dogs are bats. Some bats are cats.\nConclusions:\nSome dogs are cats.\nSome cats are dogs.', 'options': ['Only (1) conclusion follows', 'Only (2) conclusion follows', 'Either (1) or (2) follows', 'Neither (1) nor (2) follows', 'Both (1) and (2) follow'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Statements: All the trucks are flies. Some scooters are flies.\nConclusions:\nAll the trucks are scooters.\nSome scooters are trucks.', 'options': ['Only (1) conclusion follows', 'Only (2) conclusion follows', 'Either (1) or (2) follows', 'Neither (1) nor (2) follows', 'Both (1) and (2) follow'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Statements: All buildings are chalks. No chalk is toffee.\nConclusions:\nNo building is toffee\nAll chalks are buildings.', 'options': ['Only (1) conclusion follows', 'Only (2) conclusion follows', 'Either (1) or (2) follows', 'Neither (1) nor (2) follows', 'Both (1) and (2) follow'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Statements: All cars are cats. All fans are cats.\nConclusions:\nAll cars are fans.\nSome fans are cars.', 'options': ['Only (1) conclusion follows', 'Only (2) conclusion follows', 'Either (1) or (2) follows', 'Neither (1) nor (2) follows', 'Both (1) and (2) follow'], 'answer': 'd'}]

Series Completion
[{'question': '120, 99, 80, 63, 48, ?', 'options': ['35', '38', '39', '40'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': '589654237, 89654237, 8965423, 965423, ?', 'options': ['58965', '65423', '89654', '96542'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': '3, 10, 101,?', 'options': ['10101', '10201', '10202', '11012'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'In the series 2, 6, 18, 54, ...... what will be the 8th term ?', 'options': ['4370', '4374', '7443', '7434'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': '125,80,45,20,?', 'options': ['5', '8', '10', '12'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': '1, 1, 4, 8, 9, 27, 16, ?', 'options': ['32', '64', '81', '256'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': '1, 2, 3, 6, 9, 18, ?, 54', 'options': ['18', '27', '36', '81'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': '6, 13, 25, 51, 101, ?', 'options': ['201', '202', '203', '205'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': '5, 6, 9, 15, ?, 40', 'options': ['21', '25', '27', '33'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': '1, 3, 4, 8, 15, 27, ?', 'options': ['37', '44', '50', '55'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': '3, 4, 7, 7, 13, 13, 21, 22, 31, 34, ?', 'options': ['42', '43', '51', '52'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': '198, 194, 185, 169, ?', 'options': ['92', '112', '136', '144'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': '2, 3, 5,7,11,?, 17', 'options': ['12', '13', '14', '15'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': '6, 12, 21, ?, 48', 'options': ['33', '38', '40', '45'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Which term of the series 5, 10, 20, 40, ..... is 1280?', 'options': ['10th', '9th', '8th', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': '2, 5, 9, ?, 20, 27', 'options': ['14', '16', '18', '24'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': '2, 3, 3, 5, 10, 13, ?, 43, 172, 177', 'options': ['23', '38', '39', '40'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': '9, 27, 31, 155, 161, 1127, ?', 'options': ['316', '1135', '1288', '2254'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': '2, 1, 2, 4, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 8, 10, 11, ?', 'options': ['9', '10', '11', '12'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Which of the following will not be a number of the series 1, 8, 27, 64, 125,.....?', 'options': ['256', '512', '729', '1000'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': '13, 32, 24, 43, 35, ?, 46, 65, 57, 76', 'options': ['45', '52', '54', '55'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': '22, 24, 28, ?, 52, 84', 'options': ['36', '38', '42', '46'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': '3, 15, ?, 63, 99, 143', 'options': ['27', '35', '45', '56'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': '90, 180, 12, 50, 100, 200, ?, 3, 50, 4, 25, 2, 6, 30, 3', 'options': ['150', '175', '225', '250'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': '48, 24, 96, 48, 192, ?', 'options': ['76', '90', '96', '98'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': '2,15,41,80,?', 'options': ['111', '120', '121', '132'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': '6, 11, 21, 36, 56, ?', 'options': ['42', '51', '81', '91'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': '563, 647, 479, 815, ?', 'options': ['672', '386', '279', '143'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': '13, 35, 57, 79, 911, ?', 'options': ['1110', '1112', '1113', '1315'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': '1, 4, 10, 22, 46, ?', 'options': ['64', '86', '94', '122'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': '66, 36, 18, ?', 'options': ['3', '6', '8', '9'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'In the series 3, 9, 15, ...... what will be the 21st term?', 'options': ['117', '121', '123', '129'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': '28, 33, 31, 36, ?, 39', 'options': ['32', '34', '38', '40'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': '1, 9, 25, 49, 81, ?', 'options': ['100', '112', '121', '144'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': '1, 9, 25, 49, ?, 121', 'options': ['64', '81', '91', '100'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': '2,2,5, 13,28,?', 'options': ['49', '50', '51', '52'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': '0, 2, 8, 14, ?, 34', 'options': ['20', '23', '24.', '25'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': '1, 5, 14, 30, 55, 91, ?', 'options': ['130', '140', '150', '160'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'In the series 10, 17, 24, 31, 38,.....which of the following will be a number of the series ?', 'options': ['48', '346', '574', '1003'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': '240, ?, 120, 40, 10, 2', 'options': ['180', '240', '420', '480'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': '2,3,8,27, 112,?', 'options': ['226', '339', '452', '565'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': '6, 17, 39, 72, ?', 'options': ['83', '94', '116', '127'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': '20, 20, 19, 16, 17, 13, 14, 11, ?, ?', 'options': ['10, 10', '10, 11', '13, 14', '13, 16'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': '24, 60, 120, 210, ?', 'options': ['300', '336', '420', '525'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': '625, 5, 125, 25, 25, ?, 5', 'options': ['5', '25', '125', '625'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': '10, 100, 200, 310, ?', 'options': ['400', '410', '420', '430'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': '11, 10, ?, 100, 1001, 1000, 10001', 'options': ['101', '110', '111', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': '2, 7, 27, 107, 427, ?', 'options': ['1262', '1707', '4027', '4207'], 'answer': 'b'}]

Cause and Effect
Below in each of the questions are given two statements I and II. These statements may be either independent causes or may be effects of independent causes or a common cause. One of these statements may be the effect of the other statements. Read both the statements and decide which of the following answer choice correctly depicts the relationship between these two statements.
Mark answer
(A) If statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.
(B) If statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.
(C) If both the statements I and II are independent causes.
(D) If both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.
(E) If both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.
[{'question': 'Statements:\nStandard of living among the middle class society is constantly going up since part of few years.\nIndian Economy is observing remarkable growth.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThe meteorological Department has issued a statement mentioning deficient rainfall during monsoon in many parts of the country.\nThe Government has lowered the revised estimated GDP growth from the level of earlier estimates.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThe staff of Airport Authorities called off the strike they were observing in protest against privatization.\nThe staff of Airport Authorities went on strike anticipating a threat to their jobs.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nA huge truck overturned on the middle of the road last night.\nThe police had cordoned of entire area in the locality this morning for half of the day.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nImportance of Yoga and exercise is being realized by all sections of the society.\nThere is an increasing awareness about health in the society particularly among middle ages group of people.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'b'}]
Below in each of the questions are given two statements I and II. These statements may be either independent causes or may be effects of independent causes or a common cause. One of these statements may be the effect of the other statements. Read both the statements and decide which of the following answer choice correctly depicts the relationship between these two statements.
Mark answer
(A) If statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.
(B) If statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.
(C) If both the statements I and II are independent causes.
(D) If both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.
(E) If both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.
[{'question': "Statements:\nThe prices of food grains and other essential commodities in the open market have risen sharply during the past three months.\nThe political party in opposition has given a call for general strike to protest against the government's economic policy.", 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThe Government has decided to hold a single entrance test for admission to all the medical colleges in India.\nThe State Government has debarred students from other States to apply for the seats in the medical colleges in the State.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nLarge number of Primary Schools in the rural areas is run by only one teacher.\nThere has been a huge dropout from the primary schools in rural areas.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThe employees of the biggest bank in the country have given an indefinite strike call starting from the third of the next month.\nThe employees of the Central Government have withdrawn their week long demonstrations.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThe farmers have decided against selling their Kharif crops to the Government agencies.\nThe Government has reduced the procurement price of Kharif crops starting from the last month to the next six months.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'b'}]
Below in each of the questions are given two statements I and II. These statements may be either independent causes or may be effects of independent causes or a common cause. One of these statements may be the effect of the other statements. Read both the statements and decide which of the following answer choice correctly depicts the relationship between these two statements.
Mark answer
(A) If statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.
(B) If statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.
(C) If both the statements I and II are independent causes.
(D) If both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.
(E) If both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.
[{'question': 'Statements:\nMany people visited the religious place during the week-end.\nFew people visited the religious place during the week days.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nAll the schools in the area had to be kept closed for most part of the week.\nMany parents have withdrawn their children from the local schools.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThe literacy rate in the district has been increasing for the last four years.\nThe district administration has conducted extensive training programme for the workers involved in the literacy drive.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThe car manufacturing companies have recently increased the prices of mid-sized cars.\nThe Government recently increased the duty on mid-sized cars.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThe university officers have decided to conduct last examination every year in March/April in order to announce the result at proper time.\nIn past the result was declared late by the University due to the lack of number of examiners.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'b'}]
Below in each of the questions are given two statements I and II. These statements may be either independent causes or may be effects of independent causes or a common cause. One of these statements may be the effect of the other statements. Read both the statements and decide which of the following answer choice correctly depicts the relationship between these two statements.
Mark answer
(A) If statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.
(B) If statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.
(C) If both the statements I and II are independent causes.
(D) If both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.
(E) If both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.
[{'question': 'Statements:\nThe State Government has announced special tax package for the new industries to be set-up in the State.\nLast year the State Government had hiked the taxes for all industrial activities in the State.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThe government has allowed private airline companies in India to operate to overseas destinations.\nThe national air carrier has increased its flights to overseas destinations.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThe Government has imported large quantities of sugar as per trade agreement with other countries.\nThe prices of sugar in the domestic market have fallen sharply in the recent months.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nMany people in the area are reported to be suffering from Malaria.\nPrivate Medical Practitioners in the area have decided to close their clinics for few days.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nRural and semi-urban areas in the country have been suffering due to load-shedding for quite some time.\nIf the Government is not able to overcome the power crisis, load-shedding will be extended even to the urban areas.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'e'}]
Below in each of the questions are given two statements I and II. These statements may be either independent causes or may be effects of independent causes or a common cause. One of these statements may be the effect of the other statements. Read both the statements and decide which of the following answer choice correctly depicts the relationship between these two statements.
Mark answer
(A) If statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.
(B) If statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.
(C) If both the statements I and II are independent causes.
(D) If both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.
(E) If both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.
[{'question': 'Statements:\nThe Government has increased rates of petrol and diesel by 10% from the immediate effect.\nOil producing countries have decided to increase 10% of production on crude oil from the last quarter.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThe vegetable prices in the local market have increases manifold during the past few days.\nIncessant rains have created flood like situation in most rural parts of the State.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nPolice had resorted to lathi-charge to disperse the unruly mob from the civic headquarters.\nThe civic administration has recently hiked the property tax of the residential buildings by about 30 percent.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThe government has decided to give tax benefits for small savings for investments and benefit accruals. However, all withdrawals of such savings are to be taxed.\nPeople have been investing more in small savings than in equity market to avail maximum tax benefits.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThere was a huge rush of people to the temple last Sunday the 15th of the month.\nThe temple authority had decided to close down the temple for repairs from 17th of the month.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'b'}]
Below in each of the questions are given two statements I and II. These statements may be either independent causes or may be effects of independent causes or a common cause. One of these statements may be the effect of the other statements. Read both the statements and decide which of the following answer choice correctly depicts the relationship between these two statements.
Mark answer
(A) If statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.
(B) If statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.
(C) If both the statements I and II are independent causes.
(D) If both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.
(E) If both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.
[{'question': 'Statements:\nLarge number of people living in the low lying areas has been evacuated during the last few days to safer places.\nThe Government has rushed in relief supplies to the people living in the affected areas.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThe Reserve Bank of India has recently put restrictions on few small banks in the country.\nThe small banks in the private and co-operative sector in India are not in a position to withstand the competitions of the bigger banks in the public sector.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThe prices of petrol and diesel in the domestic market have remained unchanged for the past few months.\nThe crude oil prices in the International market have gone up substantially in the last few months.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThe performance of Indian sports persons in the recently held Olympics could not reach the level of expectation the country had on them.\nThe performance of Indian sports person in the last Asian games was far better than any previous games.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nLarge numbers of people have fallen sick after consuming sweets from a particular shop in the locality.\nMajor part of the locality is flooded and has become inaccessible to outsides.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'd'}]
Below in each of the questions are given two statements I and II. These statements may be either independent causes or may be effects of independent causes or a common cause. One of these statements may be the effect of the other statements. Read both the statements and decide which of the following answer choice correctly depicts the relationship between these two statements.
Mark answer
(A) If statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.
(B) If statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.
(C) If both the statements I and II are independent causes.
(D) If both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.
(E) If both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.
[{'question': 'Statements:\nThe life today is too fast, demanding all full of variety in all aspects which at times leads to stressful situation.\nNumber of suicide cases among teenagers is on increase.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThe university authority has instructed all the colleges under its jurisdiction to ban use of cell phones inside the college premises.\nMajority of the teachers of the college signed a joint petition to the university complaining the disturbances caused by cell phone ring tones inside the classrooms.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': "Statements:\nMajority of people residing in the locality have decided to protest against the municipality authority's decision to allow construction of a shopping mall in the locality.\nMany shopping malls have been opened all over the city in the recent time.", 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nThe Government has reduced the prices of petroleum products by five percent a week after increasing the prices by ten percent.\nThe rate of inflation dropped marginally during the last week.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Statements:\nPolice authority has recently increased vigil during the evening hours in the locality.\nThere has been considerable reduction in the incidents of petty crimes in the locality.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'a'}]
Below in each of the questions are given two statements I and II. These statements may be either independent causes or may be effects of independent causes or a common cause. One of these statements may be the effect of the other statements. Read both the statements and decide which of the following answer choice correctly depicts the relationship between these two statements.
Mark answer
(A) If statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.
(B) If statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.
(C) If both the statements I and II are independent causes.
(D) If both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.
(E) If both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.
[{'question': 'Statements:\nThe committee appointed by the Government on the fee structure of the professional courses has drastically reduced the fees of various courses in comparison to those charged in the last year.\nThe parents of aspiring students seeking admission to professional courses had launched a severe agitation protesting against the high fees charged by the professional institutes and the admission process was delayed considerably.', 'options': ['Statement I is the cause and statement II is its effect.', 'Statement II is the cause and statement I is its effect.', 'Both the statements I and II are independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of independent causes.', 'Both the statements I and II are effects of some common cause.'], 'answer': 'b'}]

Analogy
In each of the following questions find out the alternative which will replace the question mark.
[{'question': 'CUP : LIP :: BIRD : ?', 'options': ['BUSH', 'GRASS', 'FOREST', 'BEAK'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Flow : River :: Stagnant : ?', 'options': ['Rain', 'Stream', 'Pool', 'Canal'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Paw : Cat :: Hoof : ?', 'options': ['Lamb', 'Elephant', 'Lion', 'Horse'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Ornithologist : Bird :: Archaeologist : ?', 'options': ['Islands', 'Mediators', 'Archaeology', 'Aquatic'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Peacock : India :: Bear : ?', 'options': ['Australia', 'America', 'Russia', 'England'], 'answer': 'c'}]
In each of the following questions find out the alternative which will replace the question mark.
[{'question': 'REASON : SFBTPO :: THINK : ?', 'options': ['SGHMJ', 'UIJOL', 'UHNKI', 'UJKPM'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Carbon : Diamond :: Corundum : ?', 'options': ['Garnet', 'Ruby', 'Pukhraj', 'Pearl'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'NATION : ANTINO :: HUNGRY : ?', 'options': ['HNUGRY', 'UHNGYR', 'YRNGUH', 'UNHGYR'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Architect : Building :: Sculptor : ?', 'options': ['Museum', 'Stone', 'Chisel', 'Statue'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Eye : Myopia :: Teeth : ?', 'options': ['Pyorrhoea', 'Cataract', 'Trachoma', 'Eczema'], 'answer': 'a'}]
In each of the following questions find out the alternative which will replace the question mark.
[{'question': 'Conference : Chairman :: Newspaper : ?', 'options': ['Reporter', 'Distributor', 'Printer', 'Editor'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Safe : Secure :: Protect : ?', 'options': ['Lock', 'Sure', 'Guard', 'Conserve'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Master : OCUVGT :: LABOUR : ?', 'options': ['NCDQWT', 'NDERWT', 'NBERWT', 'NEDRWT'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Microphone : Loud :: Microscope : ?', 'options': ['Elongate', 'Investigate', 'Magnify', 'Examine'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Melt : Liquid :: Freeze : ?', 'options': ['Ice', 'Condense', 'Solid', 'Force'], 'answer': 'c'}]
In each of the following questions find out the alternative which will replace the question mark.
[{'question': 'College : Student :: Hospital : ?', 'options': ['Nurse', 'Doctor', 'Treatment', 'Patient'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Tree : Forest :: Grass : ?', 'options': ['Lawn', 'Garden', 'Park', 'Field'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'South : North-West :: West : ?', 'options': ['North', 'South-West', 'North-East', 'East'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Cloth : Mill :: Newspaper : ?', 'options': ['Editor', 'Reader', 'Paper', 'Press'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Country : President :: State : ?', 'options': ['Governor', 'M.P', 'Legislator', 'Minister'], 'answer': 'a'}]
In each of the following questions find out the alternative which will replace the question mark.
[{'question': 'Race : Fatigue :: Fast : ?', 'options': ['Food', 'Laziness', 'Hunger', 'Race'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Peace : Chaos :: Creation : ?', 'options': ['Build', 'Construction', 'Destruction', 'Manufacture'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Tiger : Forest :: Otter : ?', 'options': ['Cage', 'Sky', 'Nest', 'Water'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Poles : Magnet :: ? : Battery', 'options': ['Cells', 'Power', 'Terminals', 'Energy'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Cassock : Priest :: ? : Graduate', 'options': ['Cap', 'Tie', 'Coat', 'Gown'], 'answer': 'd'}]
In each of the following questions find out the alternative which will replace the question mark.
[{'question': 'Ice : Coldness :: Earth : ?', 'options': ['Weight', 'Jungle', 'Gravitation', 'Sea'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Parts : Strap :: Wolf : ?', 'options': ['Fox', 'Animal', 'Wood', 'Flow'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Physician : Treatment :: Judge : ?', 'options': ['Punishment', 'Judgement', 'Lawyer', 'Court'], 'answer': 'b'}]

Seating Arrangement
[{'question': 'A, P, R, X, S and Z are sitting in a row. S and Z are in the centre. A and P are at the ends. R is sitting to the left of A. Who is to the right of P ?', 'options': ['A', 'X', 'S', 'Z'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'There are 8 houses in a line and in each house only one boy lives with the conditions as given below:\nJack is not the neighbour Siman.\nHarry is just next to the left of Larry.\nThere is at least one to the left of Larry.\nPaul lives in one of the two houses in the middle.\nMike lives in between Paul and Larry.\nIf at least one lives to the right of Robert and Harry is not between Taud and Larry, then which one of the following statement is not correct ?', 'options': ['Robert is not at the left end.', 'Robert is in between Simon and Taud.', 'Taud is in between Paul and Jack.', 'There are three persons to the right of Paul.'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'A, B, C, D and E are sitting on a bench. A is sitting next to B, C is sitting next to D, D is not sitting with E who is on the left end of the bench. C is on the second position from the right. A is to the right of B and E. A and C are sitting together. In which position A is sitting ?', 'options': ['Between B and D', 'Between B and C', 'Between E and D', 'Between C and E'], 'answer': 'b'}]

Direction Sense Test
[{'question': "One morning Udai and Vishal were talking to each other face to face at a crossing. If Vishal's shadow was exactly to the left of Udai, which direction was Udai facing?", 'options': ['East', 'West', 'North', 'South'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Y is in the East of X which is in the North of Z. If P is in the South of Z, then in which direction of Y, is P?', 'options': ['North', 'South', 'South-East', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'If South-East becomes North, North-East becomes West and so on. What will West become?', 'options': ['North-East', 'North-West', 'South-East', 'South-West'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'A man walks 5 km toward south and then turns to the right. After walking 3 km he turns to the left and walks 5 km. Now in which direction is he from the starting place?', 'options': ['West', 'South', 'North-East', 'South-West'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Rahul put his timepiece on the table in such a way that at 6 P.M. hour hand points to North. In which direction the minute hand will point at 9.15 P.M. ?', 'options': ['South-East', 'South', 'North', 'West'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Rasik walked 20 m towards north. Then he turned right and walks 30 m. Then he turns right and walks 35 m. Then he turns left and walks 15 m. Finally he turns left and walks 15 m. In which direction and how many metres is he from the starting position?', 'options': ['15 m West', '30 m East', '30 m West', '45 m East'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Two cars start from the opposite places of a main road, 150 km apart. First car runs for 25 km and takes a right turn and then runs 15 km. It then turns left and then runs for another 25 km and then takes the direction back to reach the main road. In the mean time, due to minor break down the other car has run only 35 km along the main road. What would be the distance between two cars at this point?', 'options': ['65 km', '75 km', '80 km', '85 km'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Starting from the point X, Jayant walked 15 m towards west. He turned left and walked 20 m. He then turned left and walked 15 m. After this he turned to his right and walked 12 m. How far and in which directions is now Jayant from X?', 'options': ['32 m, South', '47 m, East', '42 m, North', '27 m, South'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': "One evening before sunset Rekha and Hema were talking to each other face to face. If Hema's shadow was exactly to the right of Hema, which direction was Rekha facing?", 'options': ['North', 'South', 'East', 'Data is inadequate'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'A boy rode his bicycle Northward, then turned left and rode 1 km and again turned left and rode 2 km. He found himself 1 km west of his starting point. How far did he ride northward initially?', 'options': ['1 km', '2 km', '3 km', '5 km'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'K is 40 m South-West of L. If M is 40 m South-East of L, then M is in which direction of K?', 'options': ['East', 'West', 'North-East', 'South'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'A man walks 2 km towards North. Then he turns to East and walks 10 km. After this he turns to North and walks 3 km. Again he turns towards East and walks 2 km. How far is he from the starting point?', 'options': ['10 km', '13 km', '15 km', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'The length and breadth of a room are 8 m and 6 m respectively. A cat runs along all the four walls and finally along a diagonal order to catch a rat. How much total distance is covered by the cat?', 'options': ['10', '14', '38', '48'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'One morning sujata started to walk towards the Sun. After covering some distance she turned to right then again to the right and after covering some distance she again turns to the right. Now in which direction is she facing?', 'options': ['North', 'South', 'North-East', 'South-West'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Some boys are sitting in three rows all facing North such that A is in the middle row. P is just to the right of A but in the same row. Q is just behind of P while R is in the North of A. In which direction of R is Q?', 'options': ['South', 'South-West', 'North-East', 'South-East'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'One morning after sunrise, Vimal started to walk. During this walking he met Stephen who was coming from opposite direction. Vimal watch that the shadow of Stephen to the right of him (Vimal). To Which direction Vimal was facing?', 'options': ['East', 'West', 'South', 'Data inadequate'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Golu started from his house towards North. After covering a distance of 8 km. he turned towards left and covered a distance of 6 km. What is the shortest distance now from his house?', 'options': ['10 km.', '16 km.', '14 km', '2 km.'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'P started from his house towards west. After walking a distance of 25 m. He turned to the right and walked 10 m. He then again turned to the right and walked 15 m. After this he is to turn right at 135o and to cover 30 m. In which direction should he go?', 'options': ['West', 'South', 'South-West', 'South-East'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'X started to walk straight towards south. After walking 5 m he turned to the left and walked 3 m. After this he turned to the right and walked 5 m Now to which direction X is facing?', 'options': ['North-East', 'South', 'North', 'South-West'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Hemant in order to go to university started from his house in the east and came to a crossing. The road to the left ends in a theatre, straight ahead is the hospital. In which direction is the university?', 'options': ['North', 'South', 'East', 'West'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'After walking 6 km, I turned to the right and then walked 2 km. After then I turned to the left and walked 10 km. In the end, I was moving towards the North. From which direction did I start my journey?', 'options': ['North', 'South', 'East', 'West'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Ravi left home and cycled 10 km towards South, then turned right and cycled 5 km and then again turned right and cycled 10 km. After this he turned left and cycled 10 km. How many kilometers will he have to cycle to reach his home straight?', 'options': ['10 km', '15 km', '20 km', '25 km'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Reena walked from A to B in the East 10 feet. Then she turned to the right and walked 3 feet. Again she turned to the right and walked 14 feet. How far is she from A?', 'options': ['4 feet', '5 feet', '24 feet', '27 feet'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': "One morning after sunrise Nivedita and Niharika were talking to each other face to face at Dalphin crossing. If Niharika's shadow was exactly to the right of Nivedita, Which direction Niharika was facing?", 'options': ['North', 'South', 'East', 'Data is inadequate'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'If A x B means A is to the south of B; A + B means A is to the north of B; A % B means A is to the east of B; A - B means A is to the west of B; then in P % Q + R - S, S is in which direction with respect to Q?', 'options': ['South-West', 'South-East', 'North-East', 'North-West'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'One morning after sunrise, Suresh was standing facing a pole. The shadow of the pole fell exactly to his right. To which direction was he facing?', 'options': ['East', 'South', 'West', 'Data is inadequate'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': "A child went 90 m in the East to look for his father, then he turned right and went 20 m. After this he turned right and after going 30 m he reached to his uncle's house. His father was not there. From there he went 100 m to his north and met his father. How far did he meet his father from the starting point?", 'options': ['80 m', '100 m', '140 m', '260 m'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': "Four friends A, B, C and D live in a same locality. The house of B is in the east of A's house but in the north of C's house. The house of C is in the west of D's house. D's house is in which direction of A's house?", 'options': ['South-East', 'North-East', 'East', 'Data is inadequate'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Umesh directly went from P, to Q which is 9 feet distant. Then he turns to the right and walked 4 feet. After this he turned to the right and walked a distance which is equal from P to Q. Finally he turned to the right and walked 3 feet. How far is he now from P?', 'options': ['6 feet', '5 feet', '1 feet', '0 feet'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Shyam walks 5 km towards East and then turns left and walks 6 km. Again he turns right and walks 9 km. Finally he turns to his right and walks 6 km. How far is he from the starting point?', 'options': ['26 km', '21 km', '14 km', '9 km'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Amit started walking positioning his back towards the sun. After some time, he turned left, then turned right and towards the left again. In which direction is he going now?', 'options': ['North or South', 'East or West', 'North or West', 'South or West'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Rohit walked 25 m towards south. Then he turned to his left and walked 20 m. He then turned to his left and walked 25 m. He again turned to his right and walked 15 m. At what distance is he from the starting point and in which direction?', 'options': ['35 m East', '35 m North', '30 m West', '45 m East'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Village Q is to the North of the village P. The village R is in the East of Village Q. The village S is to the left of the village P. In which direction is the village S with respect to village R?', 'options': ['West', 'South-West', 'South', 'North-West'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Radha moves towards South-East a distance of 7 km, then she moves towards West and travels a distance of 14 km. From here she moves towards North-West a distance of 7 km and finally she moves a distance of 4 km towards east. How far is she now from the starting point?', 'options': ['3 km', '4 km', '10 km', '11 km'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Sundar runs 20 m towards East and turns to right and runs 10 m. Then he turns to the right and runs 9 m. Again he turns to right and runs 5 m. After this he turns to left and runs 12 m and finally he turns to right and 6 m. Now to which direction is Sundar facing?', 'options': ['East', 'West', 'North', 'South'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Sachin walks 20 km towards North. He turns left and walks 40 km. He again turns left and walks 20 km. Finally he moves 20 km after turning to the left. How far is he from his starting position?', 'options': ['20 km.', '30 km.', '50 km.', '60 km.'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'From his house, Lokesh went 15 km to the North. Then he turned west and covered 10 km. Then he turned south and covered 5 km. Finally turning to the east, he covered 10 km. In which direction is he from his house?', 'options': ['East', 'West', 'North', 'South'], 'answer': 'c'}]

Classification
In each of the following questions, five words have been given out of which four are alike in some manner, while the fifth one is different. Choose the word which is different from the rest.
[{'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Chicken', 'Snake', 'Swan', 'Crocodile', 'Frog'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Cap', 'Turban', 'Helmet', 'Veil', 'Hat'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Kiwi', 'Eagle', 'Emu', 'Ostrich'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Rigveda', 'Yajurveda', 'Atharvaveda', 'Ayurveda', 'Samveda'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Curd', 'Butter', 'Oil', 'Cheese', 'Cream'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Potassium', 'Silicon', 'Zirconium', 'Gallium', 'Germanium'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Tea', 'Cinchona', 'Rubber', 'Cardamom', 'Chalk'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Hangar', 'Platform', 'Dock', 'Park', 'Bus stand'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Sparrow', 'Swan', 'Parrot', 'Koel'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Tall', 'Huge', 'Thin', 'Sharp', 'Small'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Pear', 'Apple', 'Litchi', 'Guava', 'Orange'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Dagger', 'Hammer', 'Knife', 'Sword', 'Blade'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Kanpur', 'Allahabad', 'Varanasi', 'Mathura'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Oyster', 'Clam', 'Scallop', 'Mussel'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Deck', 'Quay', 'Stern', 'Bow', 'Mast'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Producer', 'Director', 'Investor', 'Financier', 'Entrepreneur'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Tricycle', 'Trident', 'Trifle', 'Tricolour', 'Trilogy'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Chameleon', 'Crocodile', 'Alligator', 'Locust', 'Salamander'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Calendar', 'Year', 'Date', 'Month', 'Day'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Mumbai', 'Cochin', 'Kandla', 'Mysore', 'Vishakhapatnam'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Cumin', 'Groundnut', 'Cinnamon', 'Pepper', 'Clove'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Biscuits', 'Chocolate', 'Cake', 'Bread', 'Pastry'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Sweep', 'Wipe', 'Scrub', 'Wash', 'Stain'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Coat', 'Shirt', 'Blouse', 'Trousers', 'Sweater'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Asia', 'Argentina', 'Africa', 'Australia', 'Antarctica'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Japan', 'India', 'Sri Lanka', 'New Zealand'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Spectacles', 'Goggles', 'Binoculars', 'Microphone', 'Telescope'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Shehnai', 'Bagpipe', 'Flute', 'Sitar', 'Harmonica'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Cheetah', 'Lion', 'Bear', 'Tiger', 'Leopard'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Sheep', 'Gazelle', 'Ibex', 'Shrew', 'Tapir'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Flood', 'Hurricane', 'Avalanche', 'Earthquake', 'Explosion'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Ant', 'Bee', 'Moth', 'Midge', 'Spider'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Flute', 'Guitar', 'Sitar', 'Violin', 'Veena'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Treachery', 'Fraud', 'Deceit', 'Swindle', 'Morbid'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Lima', 'Algiers', 'New York', 'Tokyo', 'Beijing'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Reader', 'Writer', 'Printer', 'Publisher', 'Reporter'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Arrow', 'Axe', 'Knife', 'Dagger', 'Sword'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Feathers', 'Tentacles', 'Scales', 'Pseudopodia', 'Flagella'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Dog', 'Horse', 'Goat', 'Cat', 'Fox'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['House', 'Cottage', 'School', 'Palace', 'Hut'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Physics', 'Chemistry', 'Geography', 'Botany', 'Zoology'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Football', 'Volleyball', 'Cricket', 'Chess', 'Hockey'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Trunk', 'Tree', 'Fruit', 'Leaf', 'Flower'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Giraffe', 'Hyena', 'Deer', 'Rhinoceros', 'Zebra'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Poland', 'Greece', 'Spain', 'Italy', 'Korea'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Bajra', 'Mustard', 'Rice', 'Wheat', 'Barley'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Cot', 'Sheet', 'Quilt', 'Pillow', 'Blanket'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Assassinate', 'Kill', 'Kidnap', 'Stab', 'Murder'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Choose the word which is different from the rest.', 'options': ['Doe', 'Bitch', 'Sorceress', 'Drone', 'Mare'], 'answer': 'd'}]

Data Sufficiency
In each of the questions below consists of a question and two statements numbered I and II given below it. You have to decide whether the data provided in the statements are sufficient to answer the question. Read both the statements and
Give answer
(A) If the data in statement I alone are sufficient to answer the question, while the data in statement II alone are not sufficient to answer the question
(B) If the data in statement II alone are sufficient to answer the question, while the data in statement I alone are not sufficient to answer the question
(C) If the data either in statement I alone or in statement II alone are sufficient to answer the question
(D) If the data given in both statements I and II together are not sufficient to answer the question and
(E) If the data in both statements I and II together are necessary to answer the question.
[{'question': "Question: In which year was Rahul born ?\nStatements:\nRahul at present is 25 years younger to his mother.\nRahul's brother, who was born in 1964, is 35 years younger to his mother.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Question: What will be the total weight of 10 poles, each of the same weight ?\nStatements:\nOne-fourth of the weight of each pole is 5 kg.\nThe total weight of three poles is 20 kilograms more than the total weight of two poles.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Question: How many children does M have ?\nStatements:\nH is the only daughter of X who is wife of M.\nK and J are brothers of M.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Question: How much was the total sale of the company ?\nStatements:\nThe company sold 8000 units of product A each costing Rs. 25.\nThis company has no other product line.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Question: The last Sunday of March, 2006 fell on which date ?\nStatements:\nThe first Sunday of that month fell on 5th.\nThe last day of that month was Friday.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': "Question: What is the code for 'sky' in the code language ?\nStatements:\nIn the code language, 'sky is clear' is written as 'de ra fa'.\nIn the same code language, 'make it clear' is written as 'de ga jo'.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Question: How many children are there between P and Q in a row of children ?\nStatements:\nP is fifteenth from the left in the row.\nQ is exactly in the middle and there are ten children towards his right.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': "Question: How is T related to K?\nStatements:\nR's sister J has married Ts brother L, who is the only son of his parents.\nK is the only daughter of L and J.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': "Question: How is J related to P ?\nStatements:\nM is brother of P and T is sister of P.\nP's mother is married to J's husband who has one son and two daughters.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': "Question: How is X related to Y ?\nStatements:\nY and Z are children of D who is wife of X.\nR's sister X is married to Ys father.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Question: Who is to the immediate right of P among five persons P, Q, R, S and T facing North ?\nStatements:\nR is third to the left of Q and P is second to the right of R.\nQ is to the immediate left of T who is second to the right of P.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': "Question: On which date of the month was Anjali born in February 2004 ?\nStatements:\nAnjali was born on an even date of the month.\nAnjali's birth date was a prime number.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Question: How is X related to Y?\nStatements:\nY says, "I have only one brother".\nX says, "I have only one sister".', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': "Question: How is F related to P?\nStatements:\nP has two sisters M and N.\nF's mother is sister of M's father.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Question: B is the brother of A. How is A related to B ?\nStatements:\nA is the sister of C.\nE is the husband of A.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Question: How many children are there in the row of children facing North ?\nStatements:\nVishakha who is fifth from the left end is eighth to the left of Ashish who is twelfth from the right end.\nRohit is fifth to the left of Nisha who is seventh from the right end and eighteenth from the left end.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Question: How many doctors are practising in this town ?\nStatements:\nThere is one doctor per seven hundred residents.\nThere are 16 wards with each ward having as many doctors as the number of wards.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Question: On which day of the week was birthday of Sahil ?\nStatements:\nSahil celebrated his birthday the very next day on which Arun celebrated his birthday.\nThe sister of Sahil was born on the third day of the week and two days after Sahil was born.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Question: How many pages of book X did Robert read on Sunday ?\nStatements:\nThe book has 300 pages out of which two-thirds were read by him before Sunday.\nRobert read the last 40 pages of the book on the morning of Monday.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': "Question: How is Tanya related to the man in the photograph ?\nStatements:\nMan in the photograph is the only son of Tanya's grandfather.\nThe man in the photograph has no brothers or sisters and his father is Tanya's grandfather.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Question: Among T, V, B, E and C, who is the third from the top when arranged in the descending order of their weights ?\nStatements:\nB is heavier than T and C and is less heavier than V who is not the heaviest.\nC is heavier than only T.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': "Question: Which word in the code language means 'flower' ?\nStatements:\n'de fu la pane' means 'rose flower is beautiful' and 'la quiz' means 'beautiful tree'.\n'de la chin' means 'red rose flower' and 'pa chin' means 'red tea'.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Question: How many students in a class play football ?\nStatements:\nOnly boys play football.\nThere are forty boys and thirty girls in the class.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': "Question: Who is C's partner in a game of cards involving four players A, B, C and D ?\nStatements:\nD is sitting opposite to A.\nB is sitting right of A and left of D.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Question: On a T.V. channel, four serials A, B, C and D were screened, one on eacn day, on four consecutive days but not necessarily in that order. On which day was the serial C screened ?\nStatements:\nThe first serial was screened on 23rd, Tuesday and was followed by serial D.\nSerial A was not screened on 25th and one serial was screened between serials A and B.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': "Question: How is Sulekha related to Nandini ?\nStatements:\nSulekha's husband is the only son of Nandini's mother.\nSulekha's brother and Nandini's husband are cousins.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Question: Can Ritesh retire from office X in January 2006, with full pension benefits ?\nStatements:\nRitesh will complete 30 years of service in office X in April 2000 and desires to retire.\nAs per office X rules, an employee has to complete minimum 30 years of service and attain age of 60. Ritesh has 3 years to complete age of 60.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': "Question: What is the code for 'or' in the code language?\nStatements:\n'nik sa te' means 'right or wrong', 'ro da nik' means 'he is right' and 'fe te ro' means 'that is wrong'.\n'pa nik la' means 'that right man', 'sa ne pa' means 'this or that' and 'ne ka re' means 'tell this there'.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Question: Madan is elder than Kamal and Sharad is younger than Arvind. Who among them is the youngest ?\nStatements:\nSharad is younger than Madan.\nArvind is younger than Kamal.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': "Question: On which date in August was Kapil born ?\nStatements:\nKapil's mother remembers that Kapil was born before nineteenth but after fifteenth.\nKapil's brother remembers that Kapil was born before seventeenth but after twelfth.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': "Question: What is Gagan's age ?\nStatements:\nGagan, Vimal and Kunal are all of the same age.\nTotal age of Vimal, Kunal and Anil is 32 years and Anil is as old as Vimal and Kunal together.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': "Question: In a certain code, '13' means 'stop smoking' and '59' means 'injurious habit'. What do '9' and '5' mean respectively in that code ?\nStatements:\n'157' means 'stop bad habit'.\n'839' means 'smoking is injurious'.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Question: How much money do Vivek and Suman have together ?\nStatements:\nSuman has 20 rupees less than what Tarun has.\nVivek has 30 rupees more than what Tarun has.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Question: Among Monika, Anita, Sonal, Ratna and Tanvy, who came last for the programme ?\nStatements:\nMonika came after Anita but not after Tanvy.\nRatna came after Tanvy but not after Sonal.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Question: Who among P, Q, R, S and T is the lightest?\nStatements:\nR is heavier than Q and T but lighter than S.\nS is not the heaviest.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Question: How is T related to K?\nStatements:\nK has two sons; one of the sons is A.\nThe mother of T has only two sons - Aand B.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Question: What is the shortest distance between Devipur and Durgapur ?\nStatements:\nDurgapur is 20 kms away from Rampur.\nDevipur is 15 kms away from Rampur.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': "Question: How is A related to D ?\nStatements:\nB is the brother of A.\nB is D's son.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Question: Manoj, Prabhakar, Akash and Kamal are four friends. Who among them is the heaviest ?\nStatements:\nPrabhakar is heavier than Manoj and Kamal but lighter than Akash.\nManoj is lighter than Prabhakar and Akash but heavier than Kamal.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': "Question: Vinod's and Javed's salaries are in the proportion of 4 : 3 respectively. What is Vinod's salary ?\nStatements:\nJaved's salary is 75% that of Vinod's salary.\nJaved's salary is Rs 4500.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': "Question: What is Nitin's rank from the top in a class of forty students ?\nStatements:\nThere are ten students between Nitin and Deepak.\nDeepak is twentieth from the top.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Question: Which direction is Sunny facing now ?\nStatements:\nIf Sunny turns to his right and again turns to his right, he will be facing North.\nIf Sunny walks some distance and turns left and again walks some distance, then his face will be towards left of Dinesh who is facing South.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Question: T studies in which of the schools B, C, D, E and F ?\nStatements:\nT does not study in the same school as either R or J.\nR and J study in schools D and F respectively.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': "Question: How is Divya related to Shaloo ?\nStatements:\nDivya's mother is sister of Shaloo's father.\nShaloo is the daughter of Divya's grandfather's only child.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': "Question: How many New Year's greeting cards were sold this year in your shop ?\nStatements:\nLast year 2935 cards were sold.\nThe number of cards sold this year was 1.2 times that of last year.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': "Question: On which day in April is Gautam's birthday?\nStatements:\nGautam was born exactly 28 years after his mother was born.\nHis mother will be 55 years 4 months and 5 days on August 18 this year.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': "Question: What is the code for 'is' in the code language ?\nStatements:\nIn the code language, 'shi tu ke' means 'pen is blue'.\nIn the same code language, 'ke si re' means 'this is wonderful'.", 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'e'}, {'question': 'Question: Among A, B, C, D and E, who is in the middle while standing in a row ?\nStatements:\nC, who is third to the left of D, is to the immediate right of A and second to the left of E.\nC is second to the left of E, who is not at any of the ends and who is third to the right of A. D is at one of the ends.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Question: Among A, B, C, D, E and F, who is the heaviest ?\nStatements:\nA and D are heavier than B, E and F but none of them is the heaviest.\nA is heavier than D but lighter than C.', 'options': ['I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient', 'II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient', 'Either I or II is sufficient', 'Neither I nor II is sufficient', 'Both I and II are sufficient'], 'answer': 'a'}]

Arithmetic Reasoning
[{'question': 'The total of the ages of Amar, Akbar and Anthony is 80 years. What was the total of their ages three years ago ?', 'options': ['71 years', '72 years', '74 years', '77 years'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Two bus tickets from city A to B and three tickets from city A to C cost Rs. 77 but three tickets from city A to B and two tickets from city A to C cost Rs. 73. What are the fares for cities B and C from A ?', 'options': ['Rs. 4, Rs. 23', 'Rs. 13, Rs. 17', 'Rs. 15, Rs. 14', 'Rs. 17, Rs. 13'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'An institute organised a fete and 1/5 of the girls and 1/8 of the boys participated in the same. What fraction of the total number of students took part in the fete ?', 'options': ['2/13', '13/40', 'Data inadequate', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'A number of friends decided to go on a picnic and planned to spend Rs. 96 on eatables. Four of them, however, did not turn up. As a consequence, the remaining ones had to contribute Rs. 4 each extra. The number of those who attended the picnic was', 'options': ['8', '12', '16', '24'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'A, B, C, D and E play a game of cards. A says to B, "If you give me three cards, you will have as many as E has and if I give you three cards, you will have as many as D has." A and B together have 10 cards more than what D and E together have. If B has two cards more than what C has and the total number of cards be 133, how many cards does B have ?', 'options': ['22', '23', '25', '35'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'A pineapple costs Rs. 7 each. A watermelon costs Rs. 5 each. X spends Rs. 38 on these fruits. The number of pineapples purchased is', 'options': ['2', '3', '4', 'Data inadequate'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'A woman says, "If you reverse my own age, the figures represent my husband\'s age. He is, of course, senior to me and the difference between our ages is one-eleventh of their sum." The woman\'s age is', 'options': ['23 years', '34 years', '45 years', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'A girl counted in the following way on the fingers of her left hand : She started by calling the thumb 1, the index finger 2, middle finger 3, ring finger 4, little finger 5 and then reversed direction calling the ring finger 6, middle finger 7 and so on. She counted upto 1994. She ended counting on which finger ?', 'options': ['Thumb', 'Index finger', 'Middle finger', 'Ring finger'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'A man has Rs. 480 in the denominations of one-rupee notes, five-rupee notes and ten-rupee notes. The number of notes of each denomination is equal. What is the total number of notes that he has ?', 'options': ['45', '60', '75', '90'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'What is the product of all the numbers in the dial of a telephone ?', 'options': ['1,58,480', '1,59,450', '1,59,480', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'A is 3 years older to B and 3 years younger to C, while B and D are twins. How many years older is C to D?', 'options': ['2', '3', '6', '12'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'The 30 members of a club decided to play a badminton singles tournament. Every time a member loses a game he is out of the tournament. There are no ties. What is the minimum number of matches that must be played to determine the winner ?', 'options': ['15', '29', '61', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'In a garden, there are 10 rows and 12 columns of mango trees. The distance between the two trees is 2 metres and a distance of one metre is left from all sides of the boundary of the garden. The length of the garden is', 'options': ['20 m', '22 m', '24 m', '26 m'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': '12 year old Manick is three times as old as his brother Rahul. How old will Manick be when he is twice as old as Rahul ?', 'options': ['14 years', '16 years', '18 years', '20 years'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'A tailor had a number of shirt pieces to cut from a roll of fabric. He cut each roll of equal length into 10 pieces. He cut at the rate of 45 cuts a minute. How many rolls would be cut in 24 minutes ?', 'options': ['32 rolls', '54 rolls', '108 rolls', '120 rolls'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'In a class of 60 students, the number of boys and girls participating in the annual sports is in the ratio 3 : 2 respectively. The number of girls not participating in the sports is 5 more than the number of boys not participating in the sports. If the number of boys participating in the sports is 15, then how many girls are there in the class ?', 'options': ['20', '25', '30', 'Data inadequate'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'There are deer and peacocks in a zoo. By counting heads they are 80. The number of their legs is 200. How many peacocks are there ?', 'options': ['20', '30', '50', '60'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'A man wears socks of two colours - Black and brown. He has altogether 20 black socks and 20 brown socks in a drawer. Supposing he has to take out the socks in the dark, how many must he take out to be sure that he has a matching pair ?', 'options': ['3', '20', '39', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'A motorist knows four different routes from Bristol to Birmingham. From Birmingham to Sheffield he knows three different routes and from Sheffield to Carlisle he knows two different routes. How many routes does he know from Bristol to Carlisle ?', 'options': ['4', '8', '12', '24'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': "Mac has � 3 more than Ken, but then Ken wins on the horses and trebles his money, so that he now has � 2 more than the original amount of money that the two boys had between them. How much money did Mac and Ken have between them before Ken's win ?", 'options': ['� 9', '� 11', '� 13', '� 15'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'In a class, there are 18 boys who are over 160 cm tall. If these constitute three-fourths of the boys and the total number of boys is two-thirds of the total number of students in the class, what is the number of girls in the class ?', 'options': ['6', '12', '18', '24'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'A father is now three times as old as his son. Five years back, he was four times as old as his son. The age of the son (in years) is', 'options': ['12', '15', '18', '20'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': "A waiter's salary consists of his salary and tips. During one week his tips were 5/4 of his salary. What fraction of his income came from tips ?", 'options': ['4/9', '5/4', '5/8', '5/9'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'If you write down all the numbers from 1 to 100, then how many times do you write 3 ?', 'options': ['11', '18', '20', '21'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'If 100 cats kill 100 mice in 100 days, then 4 cats would kill 4 mice in how many days ?', 'options': ['1 day', '4 days', '40 days', '100 days'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Five bells begin to toll together and toll respectively at intervals of 6, 5, 7, 10 and 12 seconds. How many times will they toll together in one hour excluding the one at the start ?', 'options': ['7 times', '8 times', '9 times', '11 times'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'A bus starts from city X. The number of women in the bus is half of the number of men. In city Y, 10 men leave the bus and five women enter. Now, number of men and women is equal. In the beginning, how many passengers entered the bus ?', 'options': ['15', '30', '36', '45'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'A, B, C, D and E play a game of cards. A says to B, "If you give me 3 cards, you will have as many as I have at this moment while if D takes 5 cards from you, he will have as many as E has." A and C together have twice as many cards as E has. B and D together also have the same number of cards as A and C taken together. If together they have 150 cards, how many cards has C got ?', 'options': ['28', '29', '31', '35'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'A farmer built a fence around his square plot. He used 27 fence poles on each side of the square. How many poles did he need altogether ?', 'options': ['100', '104', '108', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'In a city, 40% of the adults are illiterate while 85% of the children are literate. If the ratio of the adults to that of the children is 2 : 3, then what percent of the population is literate ?', 'options': ['20%', '25%', '50%', '75%'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': "A is three times as old as B. C was twice-as old as A four years ago. In four years' time, A will be 31. What are the present ages of B and C ?", 'options': ['9, 46', '9, 50', '10, 46', '10, 50'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': "Today is Varun's birthday. One year, from today he will be twice as old as he was 12 years ago. How old is Varun today ?", 'options': ['20 years', '22 years', '25 years', '27 years'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'A bird shooter was askgd how many birds he had in the bag. He replied that there were all sparrows but six, all pigeons but six, and all ducks but six. How many birds he had in the bag in all?', 'options': ['9', '18', '27', '36'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': "Mr. Johnson was to earn � 300 and a free holiday for seven weeks' work. He worked for only 4 weeks and earned � 30 and a free holiday. What was the value of the holiday?", 'options': ['� 300', '� 330', '� 360', '� 420'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'What is the smallest number of ducks that could swim in this formation - two ducks in front of a duck, two ducks behind a duck and a duck between two ducks ?', 'options': ['3', '5', '7', '9'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Three friends had dinner at a restaurant. When the bill was received, Amita paid 2/3 as much as Veena paid and Veena paid 1/2 as much as Tanya paid. What faction of the bill did Veena pay ?', 'options': ['1/3', '3/11', '12/13', '5/8'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'In a class, 20% of the members own only two cars each, 40% of the remaining own three cars each and the remaining members own only one car each. Which of the following statements is definitely true from the given statements ?', 'options': ['Only 20% of the total members own three cars each.', '48% of the total members own only one car each.', '60% of the total members own at least two cars each.', '80% of the total members own at least one car.'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': "When Rahul was born, his father was 32 years older than his brother and his mother was 25 years older than his sister. If Rahul's brother is 6 years older than him and his mother is 3 years younger than his father, how old was Rahul's sister when he was born ?", 'options': ['7 years', '10 years', '14 years', '19 years'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': "A certain number of horses and an equal number of men are going somewhere. Half of the owners are on their horses' back while the remaining ones are walking along leading their horses. If the number of legs walking on the ground is 70, how many horses are there ?", 'options': ['10', '12', '14', '16'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': "Ravi's brother is 3 years senior to him. His father was 28 years of age when his sister was born while his mother was 26 years of age when he was born. If his sister was 4 years of age when his brother was born, what were the ages of Ravi's father and mother respectively when his brother was born ?", 'options': ['32 years, 23 years', '32 years, 29 years', '35 years, 29 years', '35 years, 33 years'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'The number of boys in a class is three times the number of girls. Which one of the following numbers cannot represent the total number of children in the class ?', 'options': ['48', '44', '42', '40'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'A shepherd had 17 sheep. All but nine died. How many was he left with ?', 'options': ['Nil', '8', '9', '17'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'In a family, the father took 1/4 of the cake and he had 3 times as much as each of the other members had. The total number of family members is', 'options': ['3', '7', '10', '12'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'In three coloured boxes - Red, Green and Blue, 108 balls are placed. There are twice as many balls in the green and red boxes combined as there are in the blue box and twice as many in the blue box as there are in the red box. How many balls are there in the green box ?', 'options': ['18', '36', '45', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'In a cricket match, five batsmen A, B, C, D and E scored an average of 36 runs. D Scored 5 more than E; E scored 8 fewer than A; B scored as many as D and E combined; and B and C scored 107 between them. How many runs did E score ?', 'options': ['62', '45', '28', '20'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'The total number of digits used in numbering the pages of a book having 366 pages is', 'options': ['732', '990', '1098', '1305'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'In a family, each daughter has the same number of brothers as she has sisters and each son has twice as many sisters as he has brothers. How many sons are there in the family ?', 'options': ['2', '3', '4', '5'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'At a dinner party every two guests used a bowl of rice between them, every three guests used a bowl of dal between them and every four used a bowl of meat between them. There were altogether 65 dishes. How many guests were present at the party ?', 'options': ['60', '65', '90', 'None of these'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': "Ayush was born two years after his father's marriage. His mother is five years younger than his father but 20 years older than Ayush who is 10 years old. At what age did the father get married ?", 'options': ['23 years', '25 years', '33 years', '35 years'], 'answer': 'a'}]

Verification of Truth
[{'question': 'A train always has', 'options': ['Rails', 'Driver', 'Guard', 'Engine'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': "Which one of the following is always found in 'Bravery'?", 'options': ['Experience', 'Power', 'Courage', 'Knowledge'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'A song always has', 'options': ['Word', 'Chorus', 'Musician', 'Tymbal'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Yesterday I saw an ice cube which had already melted due to heat of a nearby furnace.', 'options': ['Always', 'Never', 'Often', 'Sometimes'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'What is found necessarily in milk?', 'options': ['Cream', 'Curd', 'Water', 'Whiteness'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': "Which one of the following is always with 'Bargain'?", 'options': ['Exchange', 'Sumptuousness', 'Triviality', 'Eloquence'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': "Which one of the following a 'Drama' must have?", 'options': ['Actors', 'Story', 'Sets', 'Director'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'A boy is sitting at the back seat of a car. When the driver suddenly starts moving the car (in forward direction), the boy experiences a backward force?', 'options': ['Always', 'Never', 'Often', 'Sometimes'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': "Which one of the following is always found in 'Wonder'?", 'options': ['Crowd', 'Lumber', 'Astonishment', 'Rustic'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Disclosure always involves', 'options': ['Agents', 'Display', 'Exposition', 'Secrets'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'A bulb always has', 'options': ['Glass', 'Current', 'Filament', 'Light'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'A mirror always', 'options': ['Retracts', 'Distorts', 'Refracts', 'Reflects'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'A lotus flower always has', 'options': ['Mud', 'Petals', 'Root', 'Water'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'In India a widow can marry her brother-in-law although a man cannot marry the sister of his dead wife:', 'options': ['Always', 'Never', 'Often', 'Sometimes'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': "Which one of the following is always found in 'Remedy of fault'?", 'options': ['Punishment', 'Remedy', 'Fault', 'Scolding'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'A car always has', 'options': ['Driver', 'Wheels', 'Bonnet', 'Bumper'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'Danger always involves', 'options': ['Enemy', 'Attack', 'Fear', 'Help'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'A disease always has', 'options': ['Cure', 'Germs', 'Cause', 'Patient'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'Management always involves', 'options': ['Regulation', 'Counsel', 'Exhortation', 'Coercion'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': "Which one of the following is always found in 'Phrase'?", 'options': ['Nomenclature', 'Manifestation', 'Pictorial effect', 'Glossary'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'If we are going early in the morning towards the south the sun will be visible at our left:', 'options': ['Always', 'Never', 'Often', 'Sometimes'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'My ten years old niece is taller than my twelve years old son:', 'options': ['Always', 'Never', 'Often', 'Sometimes'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'What is always in worry?', 'options': ['Difficulty', 'Unrest', 'Non-Cooperation', 'Poignancy'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': "Which one of the following is always associated with 'tree'?", 'options': ['Flowers', 'Leaves', 'Fruits', 'Roots'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': "Which one of the following is always associated with 'justice'?", 'options': ['Hypocrisy', 'Legitimate', 'Magnanimity', 'Diminutiveness'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'A camera always has', 'options': ['Reels', 'Flash', 'Stand', 'Lens'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'What is found necessarily in a race?', 'options': ['Judge', 'Spectators', 'Competitor', 'Prize'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'What is found necessarily in game?', 'options': ['Players', 'Spectators', 'Referee', 'Victory'], 'answer': 'a'}, {'question': 'Which one of the following is always found in factories?', 'options': ['Chimney', 'Workers', 'Electricity', 'Sellers'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': 'A hill always has', 'options': ['Trees', 'Height', 'Animals', 'Water'], 'answer': 'b'}, {'question': "Which one of the following is always in 'Sentiment'?", 'options': ['Cruelty', 'Insight', 'Neutrality', 'Emotion'], 'answer': 'd'}, {'question': 'Controversy always involves', 'options': ['Dislike', 'Injustice', 'Disagreement', 'Passion'], 'answer': 'c'}, {'question': 'What is found necessarily in newspaper?', 'options': ['Date', 'Advertisement', 'News', 'Editor'], 'answer': 'c'}]
